And this cost me almost 200 million
tokens to refactor. And I'm like, "Oh, I
need to stop using Opus. This doesn't
work."
>> This is Haider Lesa, a true AWS veteran
who's trained over 8,000 architects, and
he shares his blueprint for software
engineering with agents. Today,
>> when leadership start questioning,
[music] can do I need an engineer plus
5,000 a month just for them to do their
work, that math does not add up. Even if
they forge an evidence, they forge that
they run the test, they try to copy and
paste the results from the internet,
which they do. How do I make sure that
this doesn't happen?
>> Agents and how engineering teams work
with them. We're doing something we've
never done before this episode and by
the end of it, you'll want to rebuild
your own software engineering workflow.
So enjoy.
[music]
>> The size and specifically Dublin and the
tech scene has grown quite
significantly.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> But it must be fun as well kind of the
connections you've built up and the
relationships there.
>> Oh yeah. I think uh
you typically have a company where your
formative years are typically uh there
but then Amazon was especially that the
idea of a hyperrowth or the idea of all
you need to do is a college or or this
Harvard book that you read or something
that you you'll figure it out. None of
these things worked for Amazon because
the growth was just like staggering.
Yeah. I remember um
going from like maybe a few hundred
people to like 2,000 and 4,000 people
like every year and it was like what's
going on? How where are we going to end
with this? And he was like yeah the
growth was minimum 25% year-over-year
and I was like
>> and then the head counsel was like yeah
let's double let's triple let's
quadruple and I was like
>> wow so nothing of this would work.
>> That's incredible. In the end you stayed
there 11 years. What are some of your
biggest learnings or in in which role
were they?
I have too many. Um [laughter]
I think one of the interesting things
about Amazon was even though the size
AWS specifically was
humongous in terms of size, terms of
people and processes and so forth, it
always felt like a startup in a way. So
you could move between roles and between
teams and that's some part of the reason
I suppose I was there for so long.
Before I joined AWS, I went to a meetup
of AWS, but I said I would never join a
company like Amazon, never these
enterprises. It's like I'm I'm allergic
to these things. I just want to get
something done, you know?
>> Here we are. [laughter]
>> And I remember I was complaining about
uh the presenter, but I I didn't knew no
one uh in in in the audience. And then
it was literally two guys working for
AWS like, "Hey, why don't you um apply?"
I was like, "Yeah, I'll never do this."
like no it's a bit different and so
forth. Ever since I applied and I joined
and so forth I went to maybe uh I think
eight different roles if I'm not
mistaken. So from support to field uh
customer fields like technical account
management solution architecture
specialist solution architecture then
helping build uh the what we call
serverless in the world the serverless
business. So I was uh the first
specialist outside US.
>> Mhm. So then even trying to hire like
developer advocates and everything else
I had to learn how to do the role until
we managed to hire. So all the things it
doesn't feel like Amazon from the
outside but inside it was like let's
just move let's just build these things.
So in terms of learnings
the two roles the three different roles
that were that marked I think the way I
think was something called technical
account manager. You typically are
called when things go wrong.
>> So think like we're having an outage
now. or having a big incident or you
started using AWS, you lift and shifted
and now your spend just went through the
roof and you're trying to how do I
optimize this spend? So all the all the
things that people don't really want to
they don't come nice to you and like oh
hello let me
>> the problem I have and it was just like
>> I need help now I need to solve now. So
that one was when I met companies that
people didn't want to work with
eventually. Those were kind of gaming
companies in the early days or startups
that were seeing unpreent growth. So you
would see things like
>> microservices in 2015 of these companies
or doing DevOps at scale or a API first
teams. So this was 2015. So this already
made me think okay everything should be
microservices now or DevOps or something
like this. And then the normal was
something like
>> oh 70 terabytes Dynamo DB table for
NoSQL and that was 2015. And then after
that when I started seeing other
companies a few hundred so I was like oh
they're still in the first 10 GB or
something. So like oh there's lots of
learnings [laughter] that I can share
things. Exactly. So I went from like the
trenches where everyone kind of dislikes
AWS or complain about AWS and was there
to help and fix and and try to recover
that trust in some ways
>> all the way to the first time customers
looking at AWS and they first time they
heard about elastic compute and it was
like for them it was like wow oh my god
what is this and then the specialist
role was the serverless where you went
from let's build this idea of API teams
So teams based around APIs and the
DevOps and the DevOps together and so
forth to actually your teams could be a
lot smaller because you don't have to
think about server operations or most of
the operations pieces. And that's when I
saw the second biggest shift in
learnings cuz initially I thought it's
all about tech. You just need to think
differently your dependencies how you
start your code. You have to take
performance into account. But now
performance has a return of investment
figured off to this which is developers
usually have a hard time explaining on
turning promotion cycle that if I work
on this refactor if I improve
performance of this this would have
improvement to the business. It's very
hard for developers to do this with
serless was easier. I was like well if I
do this I could cut 90% of our bills.
>> Okay.
>> And then people like really so now you
can have a line to explain something
that a CFO will be able to understand.
>> Yeah. But what I thought it was mostly
technical was like, yeah, you don't need
to use Java for everything. It doesn't
work quite well for serless back in the
days. You need to use languages like Go
or Python or Node.js.
What was interesting was for a small
team, it was all tech. But when you're
figuring things like how does this work
for 10,000 developers, how does this
work for 5,000, a thousand, or a few
hundred developers, most of it was a
organizational transformation. So
suddenly I had to witness not the not so
fun parts of organizations where you're
like what do I do now if it's 100 people
room where all they do is watching a web
server and restarting things serless
handles you don't have to do any of this
anymore all of this is gone
>> so how do you move from this do you
repurpose you retrain how do you do it
and then turns out that role for me to a
longest for the longest period was like
close to four years was How do we help
an organization to look at their own
people, look at their own teams and
start thinking about communities,
building core engineering, building
teams differently, building smaller
teams and this whole idea of road map or
PRDs back in the days was already fading
because of this model because it was so
fast. I could go to companies and do
principal engineer as a service if you
will and in 6 months you could say well
there we go got MVP we got in production
we got post-production we got some
learnings and now codifying for the rest
organization this was unthinkable in an
enterprise phase because it typically
takes years most of the work is not
coding is lo largely coordination and
then convincing people on how things
could be and how but even how things
could be is an expensive move you have
to have stakeholders that would believe
in your word that way. But when you say
actually just give me three people, I'll
show you
>> which is fun because it's a correlation
next to the AI topic which we'll talk
about it the last one. So I'll pause a
bit so I don't dominate [laughter]
the talking
>> is
seeing these companies. It was like at
some point it was like roughly 70
companies a year but I've seen a few 300
400 companies in a wheel more or less
from the inside out
>> trying to help them out becomes
management consulting becomes writing
becomes code becomes everything in
between. What I learned about services
was even though AWS would do with all
the infrastructure for them and not have
to think about anything, there was a
massive gap on I'm used to developers
take as a religion. My programming
language is Java. My programming
language is Python and nothing else
matters.
>> Identity.
>> Exactly. It turns into an identity
thing. And one of the hardest things for
them was but I'm used to Spring. I'm
used to jungle. I'm used to these
frameworks. And now I'm using
serverless. and I feel like I'm stripped
naked.
>> If I use this, I will have a cold start
of seconds, which is not good for
customers.
So, the ping I built then was something
called power tools or lambda power
tools. um which was the idea of how can
I let them use a similar developer
experience but also embed all this
normal distributed system best practices
I deponty how do you deal with poison
peeling cues how do you deal with
adaptive vitroid instead of static vitri
circle breakers you name it and that
blew up I initially thought I'll do this
for certain customers because I knew
anyways what the patterns were SDLC and
how they organize
>> but this went from like um let me just
do this prototype put in open source and
see what happens. I had no experience in
open source. I contributed hash corp
every now and then but nothing at the
size of power tools.
>> Then eventually power tools in less than
5 years no less than four years actually
we went from a few hundred downloads to
something like 230 billion API calls a
week to US government, British
government and a bunch of other places.
And I'm like, "Oh, I I cannot make a
release like like I used to. I need to
[laughter]
exactly uh so that's where I learned the
other aspects for the things I've been
learning over the years with serless and
the feud and dealing with pressure all
the time and organizational changes. Now
I had to do something fun which was
working in public. M
>> you have both sides of the coin where
everyone wants to contribute and excite
is a new tech you know like rust comes
out everyone wants to rebuild the whole
libraries like everyone else has right
and power tools wasn't so different
everyone want to contribute to build a
community from scratch but now you have
to learn how do you write in public how
do you create documentation as your your
secret source because you don't have
marketing budgets whatsoever how do you
then do product management in in the
open when everyone is criticizing and
scrutinizing how you write and how
you're thinking. How do you then on
board people that you never met and
sometimes different time zones or how do
you handle the situations where people
say I contributed this but you're not
merging my poll request and the time
that I expect because I spend my time
into this. I'm like okay [laughter]
let's have a conversation or sometimes
you have trolls on the internet that
would do a lot. I had stalking, I had a
bunch of things as well on the on the on
the downside of doing open source. So
those three roles for me were where I
learned how do I deal with production
incidents and production spend and phops
this was 2015 this idea of phops is like
yeah we were doing it [laughter] but
again I don't know everything but it was
cool to see it emerging as a a name
something you put name to things
>> then the other one was the customer
field and the serverless and how to
build a business from scratch with the
most brilliant people I can ever think
about that would work again all the way
to How do I build a principal engineer
as a service? Or how do I transform
companies, help them see this STLC
differently? And the worst which is how
do you tackle identity of developers who
are being grown attached to their
languages to their frameworks but yet
show them a path forward. And then the
last how do you then work in public use
all these skills and hats from product
marketing, engineering, customers and
everything in between.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. So that's a long but that was like
11 years.
>> No, I love that. Yeah. [laughter]
To start off, I started my career in
operations and when I hear you say kind
of that experience really resonates
seeing that side when hits the fan
when things are crucial also at a level
of scale. I wish a lot of people have
more experiences like that cuz it really
gives you perspective on
>> kind of yeah what happens when things go
wrong and it drives you or you have it
somewhere anchored in your in your brain
>> to always keep with you
>> 100%. the whole building in it public
and your open source project blowing up.
How how did that happen in the first
place? Like you you went from let's just
start this, it solves a problem for at
least what I've seen within businesses
to something that is huge and people
rely on and building in public is scary.
>> Yeah,
[laughter]
I was I think privilege is the word. I
was privileged to work on a team briefly
something called you might have heard of
something called AWS well architected. M
>> so I help build what they call AWS well
architected lens which is a way for you
to bring your own best practices for a
company for something like that and I
wrote the first one called serless lens
which also blew up by [laughter] very
quickly. Um so we had something like uh
I think it was close to 10,000 unique
reviews on different what we call
workloads more than applications per se
in 6 months and that gave me a window
into oh I can see not only the SDLC but
I can also without seeing the name aim
of the customer of course for security
reasons and legal I could see the
patterns where people were struggling
and were having issues with
observability was the first one.
Everyone had traces but there was
nothing in the traces related to the
business like so you're not really it's
not really helping you. So when the
power tools was launched was I need to
make this process easier because this
was one of those like I was telling I
was not showing I did have examples of
here's if you don't have observability
this way this is how you do it this is
how you do structure login this is how
you do everything this was 2016 by the
way
>> but there was nothing that could show a
wow moment where then in a few seconds I
could have observability I can have a
bunch of things without feeling like I
I'm having to give away testing. I have
to give away the way I do design
applications and so forth. So when I
launched power tools, it was at reinvent
um and it was supposed to be like a um a
presentation about the serverless lens
in the console of AWS which the launch
was delayed a little bit but I shared a
few things and then I said all of this
architecture best practices about
serverless security reliability and so
forth this is something I'm working on
it. So, I was intentionally using the
stage. I think it was roughly 3,000
people on stage back then to show this
is something that will help address, but
they it was it was received with half
criticism and half like super positive
feedback. the criticism came which it's
only Python like who uses Python and I
was determined to say let's make Python
the best programming language for for
serless which is power tools became
popular when I launched uh what we call
tracer metrics and um
tracer metrics and logger the structure
logging and it was so easy for people to
create demos it blew up as soon as
people start sharing in newsletters into
we call as heroes as community builders
that people started writing articles
about it how much easier it was. Then
this just created a life on its own. Uh
then the next big wave were partners not
only like Zabia but there were a few
others from AWS that started using it
into consultancies
>> to the point that people created custom
programs and consultancies implementing
power tools and it was like okay now I
lost control.
>> Exactly. [laughter] Now it just
snowballs.
>> Exactly. Yeah. Something like that.
>> Insane. Yeah. Before we go into kind of
how the software development life cycle
is evolving based on your career
experience, I'm amazed right and I
haven't even been in this field for 11
years and you've done 11 years in eight
different roles, hundreds of companies
specifically at AWS, a company that I
still look up to. I don't know about
kind of the listener listening right
now, but at least I still look up to
when it comes to their engineering
culture. Uh, and some of the people I've
spoken to that have had their tenure
there.
What would your advice be for a listener
listening to this and also thinking I
want similar experiences. I want to make
similar impact. I want my career to also
reflect that in 10 years time.
>> Mhm. I think the best advice I I saw
what came from my favorite newsletter
which is nothing related to tech but
it's something everyone needs especially
if you are a staff plus engineer. It's a
person called West Cow. Uh I'll I'll
send you the link and can share later.
It was something like when you get to
like senior plus eventually you hit a
ceiling of what else can I learn. We are
we tend to be conditioned to learn only
the hard skills and all the technical
pieces and be really good and be the
best smart person in the room which is
like BS in a way but often times when
you try to go from senior to staff or
staff to principal the hard skills don't
they matter because you have to have
otherwise you'll never get there to
begin with but they matter less because
most of the time is trying to influence
people trying to work with people trying
to communicate to people and the advice
that came from that newsletter was
That's exactly what I've been doing
without naming put a name to this which
was eventually going to hit the ceiling
and the best way to grow your career is
not to try to learn more on how to be
more effective in your own job but
trying to learn adjacent roles. So I
learned from developer marketing. I
learned from public speaking. I've
learned from how do I do business
writing? How do I write? How do I become
a tech writer? You don't have to
actually do the role to move to the
role. I was privileged. It was a great
amazing moment Amazon had and still has.
But you can join open source and start
helping out on how do I improve the
documentation. So there's a lot that you
can learn about cognitive load, how
people perceive things, how do you break
very complex topics into simple things.
Every engineer that I know, especially
at the senior level going to staff, they
always struggle with the same topic.
They go from complex to simple, never
simple to complex. So those type of
things you can learn and and you can
control your own destiny that way
without having to rely on opportunities
that your employer would probably give
you. Sometimes you can after you
exercise and open source to some other
places, but you can own that piece
yourself.
>> I like that a lot.
>> Yeah. So, it's like there's always so
many things around you. It's never a
single engineer that runs a business.
You can learn a little bit about sales,
how to influence people. At the end of
the day, we're always selling something
to someone, an idea or a thought or
trying to convince someone to the
contrarian, if you will.
>> So, those things are useful for life and
it can be useful for your career.
>> Yeah. Any career, right?
>> Precisely. Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> I did that and it was purely on interest
and instinct and curiosity. I was like,
I would love to kind of see what this
person is experiencing or
>> what's going on over there. Like I have
no clue. There's a blind spot there. Let
me try and figure that out or let me
learn more about this thing. And it's
not like I feel like people are idiots
sometimes. I just want to really
understand where certain decisions come
from. Gregor actually gave me this
advice. Gregor hope he was like when
decisions don't make sense to you like
there's very smart people there are
hardly idiots in leadership teams right
super smart people they got there for a
reason so when decisions don't make
sense it's probably some piece of
information you're missing
>> not them
>> 100%
>> and that I love because that kind of
reframed my thinking in that when
something doesn't make sense there's
something I'm missing right and I need
the bigger picture to be effective at
whatever I'm trying to achieve not just
at my job but at this team or at this
company specifically
Yeah, I I worked at Greg uh Gregory
before Amazon as well. I was lucky to
work with so many people. [laughter]
Um I used to train people to become
principal as AWS and so forth. And I
think the advice I should give them
especially people who are heavily
heavily frustrated by leadership which
sometimes comes as a spiritual being as
someone that has every knowledge but
doesn't act on anything which is a lie.
is when you don't understand something
that something feels irrational to you.
Like why are they making this decision?
Like where's the all the trail? Cuz
you're not going to find any is there's
got to be an incentive somewhere. Follow
the incentives and sometimes follow the
money. So once you do this, then you
things start to make a bit more sense.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Gotcha. Nowadays, I feel
like we're moving really fast with large
language models, agents, agentic
engineering, loop engineering. Nowadays,
there are three people in the industry
where some something they say people
resonate and then they try and figure
out, okay, where does this apply or is
this It's like it's really
funny times right now. And I see that
very effectively for the single
engineer, right? I don't have any other
responsibilities. I build, I can put my
head down, me and my swarm of agents and
we just are effective together. When it
then comes to enterprise and how this
influences the software development life
cycle, for me it's very interesting to
see how things are evolving because I
feel like everyone is experimenting and
experiencing something different and I
know you have an opinion especially with
your background and I want to dive into
that. Now we're going to do something
that we've never done before which is
also show you kind of a visualization on
screen of what it is going to talk
about. So if you're listening, you might
want to check out what we have on screen
right now. I think everything is set up
for us to do this. Can you walk me
through kind of I think starting from
product, how is product evolving with
agents in the loop nowadays?
>> Sure. Of course. I mean this is what I'm
going to show is my opinionated version
of what I know it's working.
>> Yeah.
>> But it doesn't mean is the sole truth.
Like you said, right now we're got into
a different phase of engineering. not
only engineering but running businesses
where we we are now being able to
finally hyperpersonalize anything but is
also part of the danger because then a
everyone can accidentally
wrongly assume that engineer is just a
single developer and that's all you need
or that all you need is you no longer
need PRDs or something like it and then
you're fine because an agent can do
everything for you and when there's
something called a trust and decline
recovery which I can cover more on this
topic as we go through uh the slides but
let me show you um the product first.
This is one of the loops that we we do
in in the team among at agent called the
resilience task force. And the goal here
is to try to
embed the concept of a product
requirement document. the famous or
sometimes infamous PRD. So it doesn't
become something like like as an
artifact that you you know have it and
you just point people to it and more how
do we get the essence of something like
PRD into the whole stage of product
thinking into the engineering pieces so
it doesn't become an artifact anymore
and is now a mental model for people
>> because agents will do the execution but
if you lead them wrong and astray it's a
chaos right so the whole point of this
product loop is that if you start from
discovery all the way to the slash new
work which I'll explain
This doesn't change the idea of the
discovery. If you ever were in an open
source role or ever were in my favorite
role of all times called product
engineering, then you got to have to
talk to people. You got to have to talk
to customers. Sometimes as engineers, we
always complain that requirements are
correct. I have to be do these things
again. And it's like but you can also
talk to customers. You can also get out
of the way. And this discoveries is our
way to let's talk to people first to
figure out what is it that's needed. We
need like a always does as well customer
centricity is a key. But you also don't
want to take the advice from only a
single customer. You need to have some
data and you need to start ranking and
then figure out what is this one
solution that I could do that could
tackle multiple problems at once. So
that's the discovery piece. We're trying
to figure things out, talk to people.
Then the next one becomes a whiteboard
almost like an engineering kind of a
design session where you're trying to
figure out this is what the customers
are telling you. These are the the
segments of segmentations of customers
and what kind of feature would match
this segments or this type of customers
and which feature could make more sense
to tackle 80% of them like 80 to 8020
rule the people that are getting started
versus the power users edge customers
and so forth. M
>> so the whiteboarding is for us to start
figuring out what is it that a road map
could look like because now with agents
the whole idea of let's do this quarter
quarterly plan or yearly plan is mostly
collapsed but again not everywhere. So
how do you do this in a whiteboard first
so it fits in your brain and then
eventually we have to codify this into
an actual road map into something. Yeah.
But we also don't want to turn this into
a waterfall like because it's also very
common these days especially with
specdriven development that's not a
problem but how we approach specdriven.
So we take everything that's in the
whiteboard and we call a assistant it's
called /romap
>> before we go there. So discovery and
whiteboard are those still the same
people doing that because from my
perspective it will be product people or
people responsible for their product
specifically.
>> That's the beauty of product
engineering. um if you have a product
manager with you and with the team
amazing have a superpower
>> but it's not always the case especially
if you're in a startup or if you're in
certain places. So in the team that we
we have the resilience task force which
sometimes we refer as RTF to make things
easier.
>> Um we don't have the product manager.
We're actually getting someone now which
is super cool.
>> Okay.
>> Um but engineers are all staff plus
engineers. So they're expected to have
some of that skills. Uh so I most of the
time act as one when I need it. So I
would guide some of those discussions
with customers and bring another friend
with me uh staff engineer as well to
figure out what is it that they're
saying and do use some of the normal
techniques about ranking UX journey and
some of the things as well.
>> Yeah. When you mentioned kind of looking
into responsibilities adjacent to your
role if you're a software engineer. This
is a perfect example of that, right?
>> Absolutely. Even the idea of like a tech
lead, I think some of the industry back
in the days used to codify this into oh
a tech lead would know but a product
engineer would equally be able to do it.
>> This is why it's my favorite role
because you can merge both customerf
facing aspects of engineering dealing
with customers thinking about product
road map what is the outcome I want not
implementation etc. Most of the time
coding you don't want to do it because
you're going to have to maintain. So if
you don't if you sell something without
code amazing even better.
[clears throat]
>> Exactly. Even better. And but then you
also need to be the the voice of uh I
wouldn't say truth but the voice of
reason sometimes of this this outcome is
amazing in the business but to be able
to implement this is going to be very
costly. So you have to have that
technical background. So product
engineer end up doing both. So if you
manage to get those skills this agencies
like becomes like I can do even faster.
>> Gotcha. Yeah. Then we have the SL road
mapap where for the first time this is
where you have the plus agent next to a
human. Yeah, pretty much the reason the
reason for this is that
I think I was trying to find a word
that's more kind [laughter] to describe
what I read on the internet sometimes is
that when we are using models for so
long using the words like please using
the words like could you think about
this it's like waste of tokens but
eventually that makes your brain should
think that this is how you communicate
now but it's not really the way so force
Since you have no agents whatsoever
first and think about what the customer
problem is, it forces you to use more of
an analytical brain and use more of a
different kind of skew set that
otherwise you wouldn't. So I wanted to
have this so your human aspects the
empathy pieces that drives you for even
better solutions don't atrophy
>> in a way. So this road map is now still
part of big part which I explain now but
the having agents first I initially
started with this and then realizing
that my communication became more tur
and more direct and I was like why am I
doing this I I'm not rude I'm not that
kind of person and it just happens to
all of us no matter the background of
experience you have
>> yeah so the critical thinking especially
on the early side understanding customer
problems and also using your language as
such that stays with the human Yeah,
pretty much. Pretty much. Yeah, if
you're looking as a staff or as a
principal,
>> the biggest identity crisis that
principles engineers have, especially
staff, is like they move from let me
just code this to oh, English is now my
new programming language and it's hard
for people to accept. It can get
different impact. It's complicated.
>> Gotcha.
>> But another day we can talk more about
[laughter] this. Now, for the slash road
map, it's like a stupidly simple. The
idea of a slash road mapap is a command
that would try to take whatever input
you have on a whiteboard or notes or
something to try to update or create a
road map like a markdown road map.
Nothing really complicated and that
would have these are some of the phases
or ideas that I have or milestones if
you will and once you have this then you
can say let's go ahead and sync this to
whatever system we use GitLab, Jira, you
name it. in our case is GitLab and this
creates epics, creates issues but one of
the major wins for having a SL road map
is that sometimes especially engineers
again we forget that we're going to have
to have some level of acceptance
criteria or what is the outcome that we
want.
>> Yeah.
>> So road map enforces this because then I
can use this into the developing loop. I
have another loop just to verify have we
actually achieved the outcome we wanted
otherwise none of the code and the test
matter.
>> Gotcha. And the slash means it's a skill
or it's something that's preconfigured
that helps you with that.
>> So this is a command. So we use a a
company called factory. It's a factory
droid. It's like cloud code. There's
many companies like this like the
amazing open code and so forth as well.
>> But the idea is that we have the
definition of a command which is
something that's user invoked
>> and you have the skill which is a more
of a model invoked. I keep having mixed
results with skills because at Rajin we
are true believer of using multiple
choices experimenting a bunch of things
>> and we not we don't use only like a claw
for instance opus or something like it
we use I think it was in my account it
was roughly 32 different models
>> oh cool
>> which is a lot of different models so
their their experience and the quality
varies a lot it's great for um token
efficiency and budget which we'll talk
about it But when it comes to having his
skills everywhere, what I notice is that
eventually you have many things that
models simply skip or they say they're
doing it, but they're doing completely
different. So a command forces to
>> to actually use it.
>> Yeah. And this works, I think, more in
an augmented way, right? Where the human
is still in the driver's seat, they say,
"Okay, right now we do this because we
use a command instead of a skill." And
then when you go more towards autonomous
AI, that's where the model makes the
decision on okay based on the context we
now apply X Y and Z in skills.
>> Yeah, pretty much. I'm a big fan of
because of everything explained to
organizations and so forth is that
humans are nondeterministic by nature.
>> Mhm.
>> But now we're adding more agent which is
even more nondeterministic. So I need
some level of determinism. So this is
latch commands make sure that I know
these instructions will be followed to a
certain degree.
>> Gotcha. Yeah. What's next? The next one
is uh I briefly talked which is now that
you have a road map you typically going
to it's going to create this roadmap.mmd
docs whatever folder structure and then
you have a sync of this road map you
typically ask you but if it doesn't you
have a /ro woman--sync
and that will create all this epics all
these issues and update the road map so
in case you run it again you know we
don't determinism you know I want you to
keep creating more epics or something
the issue with this commands for product
management what I noticed
was
now create go ahead and create epics and
issues and then the next time you run it
oh actually going to create the ones
very similar very because I think the
context is right there and then it keeps
on tripping itself so the idea of having
a separate one or a separate subcomand
is to make sure that these are more
deterministic
>> gotcha and are these epics sub items the
breakdown of the problem we're trying to
solve which is going to result in a
feature or feature set is the product
person or the and even the product
engineer defining what that looks like
or is the agent helping with how to
break down this bigger piece of problem.
>> It's both. That's why I put the human
and agent.
>> Yeah,
>> that's when you mentioned augmenting I
think is my almost new favorite word in
a way. Um
>> even as humans there's so many things
that we can think about it. Um one of
the things we do a lot at a especially
with this project is doing adversarial
reviewers. So whenever you have a road
map or have a plan, a spec or something,
you always run a multiple angles of
contrarians uh review if you will to see
if you miss anything, if there's
something you're maybe overengineering
or if you're trying to boil the ocean to
a degree. So we have that element, but
it's not so
um enforced or so hard as a requirement.
It's it has a it has a instruction to
say after the road map has been finished
do a pass like a mini loop to see if
some of those are similar and they can
be merged or if some of those don't have
clear outcome or clear acceptance
criteria and interview using socratic
method until we actually get to the
bottom of this is the thread this is how
you think this is your rationale and
these are invariance and now we know
what the product needs
>> but even in doing all this you're never
going to Yeah, 100%. This is some of the
things that we do to make it easier
>> to make also people. I think I would
love to have this. I'm right now
responsible for product and to have
something where and I do do this with my
peers, but it's not really like
structured as such, right?
>> It's kind of free flowy right now. And
it feels like you have more of a process
to make sure that the outcomes and also
the people determining the outcomes are
better at that.
>> Yeah, I think again privilege.
[laughter]
I think this came from this cooling of
Amazon to a degree. Uh because Amazon
was very heavy on writing. So you
wouldn't be able to get an idea out
until you had something on paper. So you
had to convince people through a
document, not through a presentation. In
many ways, this was amazing because it
wasn't whoever spoke the loudest would
actually win, but whoever had a the most
clarity of thought, if you will. But it
was also hard because not everyone would
be able to read or write to to a degree.
I spent like four maybe six years
training on just on writing which was
like a lot of time. Not everyone has
that time
>> and uh and for this when I try how do I
bring this to a a gentic word and how do
I bring this without turning into Amazon
or some of the toxic pieces that
sometimes happens in writing. So the
quickest trick even if you don't have
much of a process is to always tell the
agents use the socratic method to get to
the bottom or find holes in my thinking
my clarity and so forth and that alone
forces it to be more structured.
>> What do you mean with the socratic
method or how can you explain that for
the listener? Yeah. So the Socratic
method is come from philosophy where
you're trying to get to an understanding
of a topic truly simply by asking
questions and you one question leads you
to another question another question and
you're trying to see if there are
discrepancies is in their thoughts as
you're trying to ask a question.
eventually you it's not that you run out
of questions but you run out of threads
that you find these discrepancies and
where they say things that actually it
kind of goes against what you said in a
previous statement and so forth. So the
Socratic method is a way for you to
almost like an investigation mode but
through a curiosity lens. You're trying
to understand something to the fullest
but without make it seem like you are
interrogating someone and they committed
a crime and they have to tell you
something now.
>> Yeah. So when you have the kind of peer
review, this is the method they use only
questions. They're not people that say
they have a question and then also give
their opinion. And you can do this with
an agent as well, I'm assuming.
>> Yeah, pretty much. I at Amazon I had a
role which was super cool was a almost
engineer as a service. And I had
something called discovery [laughter]
which is where some of the name come
from. And I had to figure it out within
one week a company would tell me that um
they they were unable to ship fast
enough which is like vague like there's
so many things never a technical reason
or that they are engineers are not
actually doing something as they thought
it was the quality is not there maybe
they need to think about hiring
externally so they wanted a second
opinion and in that one week I had to
interview people I had to talk to people
like almost like a consultant in a way
and one of techniques was basically
saying we're going to go for 90 minutes
and I'm going to ask you a few questions
for 70 minutes or so, but here's the
game of the here's the rule of the game
and you you tell me if I'm being
dishonest. I would not show my opinion.
I will bring no bias whatsoever. Even
though it's almost impossible human in
judgment, but my role here is to try to
understand your point of view and try to
get to the bottom of how you think.
What's your mental model? what is your
view of the word and then I use
photocratic method to simply keep asking
questions and then playing back and try
to show them in the last 20 minutes of
the meeting. This is what I understood.
Did I take it wrong? Did I take it
something else? And then I would repeat
until I get a view of okay this is where
basically patterns what agents do pretty
well and these are the things that it
sounded true from a position of power or
a position of management or you name it.
But when you start digging it, there's a
lot of misconceptions, misinformation,
or lack of transparency, which open
source kind of solves it.
>> Gotcha. It seems like a very interesting
skill that I can also just put into
practice and experiment with, right? I
don't have to say I'm going to now use
Socratic method, [laughter]
but I can just keep asking questions and
hopefully it's not in an annoying way
where people kind of drill down their
thoughts and we get clarity on what they
actually want to do in that way.
>> Yeah. And that's basically what I'm
doing with agents. I'm actually forcing
agents to do this with me. And sometimes
it becomes annoying because they're
like, "You're doing this to me.
[laughter] Don't do what you're doing."
>> Um, but I think what it's what's amazing
about this is that we the more
experience you have, the easier it
becomes for you to jump into
conclusions, the quicker it becomes. Oh,
I've seen this before. And you think the
word re revolves around this
>> using the idea of socratic methods or
let's say let's do an investigation for
70 minutes just questions like if I'm
being too hard or too aggressive let me
know and then I'll
lower some of the intensity if you will
but setting the expectations up front
and having nothing but paper notes and
asking questions it helps a lot.
>> Yeah you also do this with paper notes
interesting. Yeah, I
one of the roles I had. Sorry, there's
just too much.
>> No, [laughter] that's okay. Yeah.
>> One of the one of the when I moved from
Oh my god, you're here. Let's solve
everything. Production is down. No,
>> lifesaver.
>> Yeah. Or sometimes it was also like a a
a
>> scapegoat. [laughter]
>> Exactly.
>> It's you. It's you.
>> Exactly. Um when I moved to the other
the completely contrasting version of
this which was something called solution
architect which we nowadays we call like
forward deploy engineer in a way I had
to go to those customers and it was the
first time ever they saw me and they
were like oh my god it's amazing so
forth but there was so much that they
wanted to share or worse sometimes we
because it was this was commercial world
so I needed to I always had a account
manager with me which I learned heaps on
influence in sales and I and I saw Oh,
sales is not this thing that you just
want to sell something like you're
building relationships like oh okay and
the the secrets was the paper what I
learned through the role was I was
always have a premeating just before
that very important meeting let's call
high stake meeting so I would use my
paper to prep two or three questions
ahead of time prep a part where I would
always say these are the main takeaways
or main actions we're going to do it and
then go around it and what I've noticed
after the few years of doing only pay I
only do paper by the way only do paper
notes nowadays
>> still
>> still yeah it's I started to look
differently when I go to meetings I see
people with laptop I'm like oh I know
they're not going to pay their fullest
attention to this
>> because there's always a wall between
you and this thing even though it
doesn't people don't really intend to to
come this way but it comes this way it's
natural
>> and with paper you're basically there
you're open so in a more in I wouldn't
say empathetic way but It gives you an
advantage because you can see body
language. You can see typically what 70%
plus of the communications body language
is not as non-verbal but not body
language per se.
>> So using paper gives me two advantages
that I will never get on laptop. On
laptop I would always type faster than
my thoughts are able to process and
digest information which is a
disadvantage. On paper is the opposite.
I'm always writing slower because I'm
processing I'm already digesting that
information. On laptop I usually take
notes and then I have to spend another
time thinking about what is it that I
typed what is it that I understood and
took from paper I do this simultaneously
there's something called dual theory can
talk about these things but it gives me
something the laptop would never give me
which is I can ask you a question like a
leading question or mirroring something
you did to me and as you answer the
question I might already have two or
three other questions lined up or I can
write down a question should not
interrupt you. So your flow keeps
naturally and maybe you already answered
the question I was going to ask. So I
just cross and that conversation becomes
more natural and it feels like on the
other other side you've been heard you
build a connection and with paper they
can do this very quickly. So I can guide
the conversation whichever place we want
it to be
>> without feeling like I'm coercing you or
doing something like in a bad way. I
have realized this blockade that a
laptop can form and sometimes when
guests share something I'm like I I I
want to try this out and I have this
inkling of I want to try this out but I
also don't really like writing in the
whole paper note like what I try and do
this is my approach genuinely and it
really depends on the context cuz
sometimes I do need to take notes on the
fly I try and remember as much as I can
>> and this probably this setting of
podcasting and kind of being in the seat
of hosting and asking questions and
driving really helps with me memorizing,
internalizing, and like picking a thread
up after it's been dropped later.
>> Um, but that's my approach. And then as
soon as that meeting ends, if it was an
important one, I go and I take my notes
[laughter] cuz I also want to kind of be
able to revisit them. And right now, I
do typing less and less. So, as soon as
I'm done, I go click
>> speech to text, let's go, random
thoughts here and there. And as I'm
speaking that I feel like might be
comparable to what you mentioned when
writing I also gain clarity because I
can type quite quickly and it can be
quite rough notes just here and there
and here and there but when I'm speaking
I'm trying to articulate well. So then
all of a sudden I need to have my
thoughts in order which means I need to
slow down the way I speak and actually
have clarity in my thinking.
>> That's that's precisely why we use paper
notes because a way is a forcing
function if you to slow down. We always
had this problem before agents and now
we have agents even more. We have more
information than we can know what to do
with it.
>> Yeah.
>> And being able to reason about something
and then
>> getting a step ahead. This is what paper
will give you. So a simple trick next
time you just take a normal page of
paper, count five lines from uh from the
bottom of the page, just draw a
horizontal line and there all you're
going to do is write in your questions.
But don't write an entire question cuz
it's impossible. They're not going to be
fast enough. Otherwise they're going to
be we're speaking
[laughter] it makes it feel worse. So
what what you would do is you will write
a keyword or something that reminds you
what the question you want to ask and
then you ask and then it goes and then
you already have a second question as
they are speaking that makes it more
natural.
>> Gotcha.
>> There not the raw paper notes is not for
you to type everything as is. Yeah.
>> But just for the thought of you thinking
this is the question I want to ask more
or less the frame. this is the next
items that we should be crossing after
the meeting ends or something. It's more
than enough. You don't need to take lots
of what is it that they said cuz the
whole goal is for you to be there, be
present, have a good positive image in a
way
>> and then I basically achieve something
or agree to something.
>> The only reason we have meetings which
some of the developers hate is that we
always think differently. We always have
different points of view. So a meeting a
good successful meeting always have
something I love which is why are we
meeting to begin with what is the
success criteria so when you go to a
meeting everyone knows this is why we're
here if we don't cross this then this
meeting especially if it's recurring
>> should be canceled
>> failed
>> exactly it hasn't served his purpose but
if it has then fantastic now you have
your notes what the next action should
be and perfect so this idea of taking
notes is to give you the advantage of
you can now read the table. There's
other techniques you can also use in
sales which is super cool. Uh but you
can use the reading of the table and you
forcing to slow down. So now you can
understand how people say certain
things. If you type that person says
certain things, but how did they feel?
Were they pissed? Were they actually
more positive? Were they like, "Yeah,
that's how we do." It says a lot more
than what you're going to capture as a
note if you were to um almost like in a
police station have a scriber just
typing it. We're not scribbers,
>> right? We're supposed to have that
understanding and know where to go next.
>> Yeah, that explains a lot to me cuz I
was thinking of writing out my full
question on paper and being like, I'm
way too slow of a writer. I need to get
f faster at writing if I even want to
try this. But keywords is what I do when
I do do it on a laptop as well. So then
it would make sense to try this. I am
going to try this. I think it's gonna be
fun.
>> Please do. After your podcast, I'll show
you some of my favorite notes.
>> I I was even thinking, should I then do
this in a podcast setting? Should I just
be like, there you go.
>> I actually did when I used to do
streaming and such, I used to do it as
well. Yeah, it's very quick. Uh it's
like a reporter like it's you.
It's those are the things that you like,
oh man, I never thought about this way.
It's just like, have you ever seen a
reporter bringing a laptop for an
interview? They will never do this. They
would always have something like quick
paper notes or something. Yeah,
>> that's why.
>> Gotcha. Yeah, we talked about breaking
down from discovery a problem that you
have and breaking them down into epics
or issues some form that is more
digestible. What comes after that?
>> So now that we have the road map, one of
the main things that happen is this
sense of judgment of have I actually
captured everything cuz humans want to
have I wouldn't not every human has a
sense of perfectionist. I do
>> which is a problem. uh and I built
mechanisms to prevent me from be
[laughter]
perfectionist in a way otherwise I get
nothing done. um you got a road map but
the normal sense it would be especially
for the engineer like what if I start
implementing this halfway through I
figure oh I missed something or I didn't
have the clarity of thought that I
thought I had because sometimes when you
get actual code you find more things
even if you spoke to customers hundreds
of hours it's normal then we have
something called slash new work which is
also another command so what that does
is to bridge that gap when you're
implementing something or especially the
biggest problem now with agents is like,
"Oh, just just one more thing. I can
just do it. It's so cheap now.
>> Do you want me to do it? It even asks
you."
>> Exactly. It's like, "No, don't don't
don't feed my my toxic personality in
[laughter] that in that sense."
>> One more thing.
>> Exactly. No, don't do this. It's not a
Steve Jobs type stuff type of stuff. And
um sometimes you want to capture that
thought so you you do it later or
sometimes it's literally a hole into the
plan but it's not a hole that you could
have prevented from the to begin with.
It's something you only realize when you
are in the process of implementing or
doing something. So slash newwork takes
of your context and then you can say you
know what I just found this but sounds
like we need an issue for this and then
he creates a new GitLab issue or J
whatever and he associates with an epic
so work always remains traceable.
>> Gotcha.
>> So you can do this throughout
implementation or you know it's a new
session let me just do this because we
don't have it. So you can use both ways.
>> Interesting. I am a person that for some
things I'm a little bit more
perfectionist
but for some things and especially when
it comes to the way we software engineer
I feel like we need a certain level of
pragmatism because as you go and as you
start you learn new things and sometimes
90% of the way is actually perfect and
you keep it that 100% because the last
10% will never be prioritized.
>> Mhm. That's my approach so far to a
point where sometimes I'm even like too
much on that way of thinking and that
black and white.
>> Um so I also need people to
counterbalance that and be like well
this is still actually very important
for x y and z reason. So yeah, this
would I think be quite interesting.
>> But this is the beauty of u this is
where um I don't I don't like when
people say, "Oh, I'm using agents and
I'm now 20 100 times productive like in
a single setting or in a team setting
because we don't work alone. Uh even if
you say you work alone and you're
working on a single open source that you
do everything on your own, eventually
people are going to consume and ask you
questions. So you're still going to have
some level of collaboration. So for me
when building teams back in the days it
was always trying to pull uh pull people
by their strength and see what adds up
as opposed to oh this people could only
do this. What is it that actually add to
the team?
>> Mhm.
>> Because I if I were to build a team I
would definitely want someone like you
to start going through hang on a second
we're trying to boil the ocean. Let's be
a little bit more pragmatic in here to
get the task and get the job done. But I
would also want to have someone who
would be like have we really thought
about every single corner case? Have we
done a formal verification which is one
of the hardest things to do in
engineering uh to cover the last 10% or
last 5% if you will cuz sometimes there
are critical mission critical
applications where these things are not
a nice to have. These are table stakes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I like that a lot.
It's really dependent on the use case
which mindset you need and having a
combination equipped kind of within a
team allows you to be very versatile on
the problems you solve.
>> Yeah. And I and I had this conversation
this week with a with a very senior
engineer trying to understand a reorg in
something that happened without going
into the internals because there's no
point in sharing. But engineers would
typically see a reorg as oh another
reorg. Oh my god. like we're going to
change it again. We don't have focus.
But sometimes this organization is a
living organism as well like software
and so forth that the moment you change
something you might you you might not
have the full picture like the pieces
we're discussing. They don't understand
leadership don't understand what they're
doing so forth but it's only preparing
the organization before it makes another
change significant pieces like we're
doing software. You're not going to
simply say agent go ahead and refactor
everything to rust because I love rust.
It might work. It might run out of
credits. It might have it might be
chaotic. Yeah. But you're trying to do
to make this more deterministic is
you're trying to prep the code base so
the agents understand these are this the
patterns that work. These are the things
they should not do. These are the things
that should actually be caught by a link
and not by adversarial reviewer.
Otherwise, you're spending too much time
on nondeterminism. And then once you
have this and now you make one change,
does it work? And then you make the
other one.
>> Gotcha. Yeah.
When engineers then actually pick up an
item, something that needs to be done,
what does that look like?
>> It's very similar to let's call it the
traditional way. You pick up an issue
and then you say agent go do the task
>> and the agent will because the issue has
already a template you already know that
I'm structured. An issue would already
have a template and already have to say
these are the outcomes. These are the
basically what the acceptance criteria
is, what the problem is. uh way
potential solution if there's one and
they will simply use the agent to drive
everything and they would have a
conversation of uh how do I how do I get
this to work in implementation is this a
solid use case is this a does it have
tradeoff or something like this maybe
this is a good hooking point to go to
the next slide to show you what a
development look uh cycle looks like
>> let's do that
>> it's more complicated than it looks I
try to make it as simple as possible but
we use a project called openspec which
is uh one of my favorites when it comes
to specdriven development. The idea of
opensp spec like anything related to
specdriven development is you are having
a discussion a brainstorming phase first
where trying to figure out what the
solution could look like. Do we need a
database? Do we need a persistence
layer? Do we need testing? How do we
test this thing? Do we use ports and
adapters? Do we use hexagonal
architecture? How do we make this
evolvable? There's so many questions
that you're using and this openspec
explore uses socratic method to try to
keep asking you until they get to the
bottom of what your design looks like.
It's never going to be 100% but it gets
you to a good enough
>> how do I test this? How do I structure
the code base or this feature? So the
when I read the files
>> I know what the role is and I can see
some level of architecture. So the
explorer is brainstorming of the task.
But sometimes that's the pragmatism that
comes in. You don't need all this
heavyweight machinery just to do uh
change the color of something or you
know what just add a drop down. It makes
no sense to have an entire open spec uh
pieces into it. So then you can simply
prompt your way out
>> and then we have verification layers
later to say
>> have we actually achieved the outcome as
we wanted as described in the issue as
described in the road map. So you remove
the pressure off the the individual the
engineer and also the agent to get
everything perfect.
>> Gotcha. Openspec I I've experimented
with and if you're listening we have a
new image on the screen that shows the
developer loop I would say.
>> Yeah.
>> So it starts with exploring.
>> Yeah. That would be an agent and a
human. It says also sot which is
state-of-the-art model.
>> Exactly.
>> So you would do this with the higher
capable models in exploring what issue
needs to be built.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> One of the differences uh at a which I
love by the way is that we're not the
type of company that will just use
something for the sake of using an hype.
We're mostly trying to think about what
is it that would solve the merchants's
problem. How do we make the merchant uh
use this technologies or something for
to get better margin loyalty you name it
there's all the kinds of problems we
want to get and when it comes to AI we
could technically use sot only the oppos
and only like GPT 5.5 or something like
it but that eventually comes with a cost
and you're not similar to the the jargon
that developers use the best tool for
the job you don't want to use this all
the time so in our process we usually
use three different tiers of models. We
use a let's call the best model sa
>> for help me understand help me explore
don't do anything don't create any files
like you're prohibited to create
anything you have to ask for permission
before you create anything there's hooks
there's something we can prevent it and
this is where I find those very large
models super efficient especially if you
use something like fable which is
amazing at planning things so once you
have a plan out and you go to let's say
implementation then you can use more of
a mid tier depending on what you planned
and then can use smaller models,
especially open weights, super effective
to do rounds and rounds and rounds of
reviews. So your
>> your your finance appreciates and then
you can also make more efficient use of
budgets which is something that we're
now still getting good grips of it in
the age of the AI now. Right now we're
getting into like yes use everything
token maxing which is not my the thing I
I'm a fan of [laughter]
but eventually that that cost will come
and then when leadership start
questioning hang on a second do I need
an engineer plus 5,000 a month 3,000 a
month just for them to do their work
that that math doesn't doesn't add up
for a one engineer few engineers sure I
mean companies like it's a pocket money
>> especially in an enterprise but when
you're looking at the scale of a for
instance like 1.4 4,000 engineers that
we have that math starts to show very
quickly and ask questions. But it's not
that we would be like we would never do
this, but we have to be more sensible.
Something we're still figuring out.
Nobody has the final answer to all this
otherwise they would have sold it for a
few years.
>> Yeah. We would have we would have been
[laughter] using it already. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Exactly. In this idea then
specifically do you envision this is
going to be a a guidance a guideline
education on how we work as software
engineers within software development
life cycle specifically in your
environment in your org or are you going
to enforce this to a certain degree
because 1400 people having the ownership
lie on them on this is how we work and
then them also having the ability to not
do that and to only use state-of-the-art
models kind of I'm wondering what your
thought pattern is there. Yeah,
I came from cloud. [laughter] So the
first not cloud but audience would
understand it. In cloud computing the
first shock that most organizations had
was I knew exactly what I would pay in
my server even with like thousands of
money.
>> Yeah.
>> And then you would depreciate over x
amount of years, right? X number of
years.
>> Simple math calculation. You got it.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Which it sounds simple
like Yeah. It's capex versus opex type
of thing. And then cloud is like what do
you mean? I don't know what my bill
exactly is going to be next month. This
doesn't sound correct.
>> There you go. Let's go. [laughter]
>> Exactly. So when you see the
productivity and and what you get from
cloud electricity and self-service and
so forth, you're like, "Oh, I get it."
But I also don't want to make this for
everyone because it may not make sense.
It it comes to a point where you have to
trust human judgment otherwise why did
you hire the person to begin with? But
then you also have to have some level of
guard rails on top of advices uh
patterns software to kind of help you
when it comes to AI especially at a we
have a platform engineering organization
that we have an amazing team just focus
on this right now. So one of the main
points from them is to figure out how
does the SDLC the software development
life cycle looks like in a gentic area.
What is it that we have to create as
paved roads? Something that we know. But
it's never going to be a single paved
road. It's going to be paved roads
depending on our profile, depending on
the application. Is this a web hook? Is
this in the critical flow? You're taking
fraud. You're not going to reduce tokens
for something that's going to be a
fraud. It's like a huge thing. Uh but
also how do what tools do we use? Uh one
of the main issues with AI now right now
is like oh I can use open code.
Sometimes I use cloud code. Sometimes I
use something else. kilo kilo from
Amazon. It's all over the place. Like
cloud was the same. It was no different.
But in this case, you're trying to what
we're doing at Aggin specifically is
trying to find those the normal uh the
settlers and um the idea of
organizations where you find who are the
people that are exploring things that we
want to keep a close eye to learn what's
working, what's hype, what doesn't.
That's part of my team's doing as well.
And now that we got this, how do we
experiment with two, three more teams
off of these experiences? Do we use
opensp spec? Do we use something else?
Like opensp spec works for part of a
majority of agent does not work at all
because we have a gigantic monor repo
>> which is not a bad thing. They have all
the context there, but the agents don't
quite like at times
>> because it's too much and openspec
doesn't quite have the idea of working
in a monor repo. It thinks that
everything's going to be in a top level
folder. But when you're having hundreds
and thousands of developers touching
these things, get conflict happens and
everything else happens. So how do we
make it work now for a m a population of
developers and then how do we
transition? How do we step onto this
larger monor repo? So it works for the
majority the core business of a for
instance. So we have this team thinking
about the things
>> thinking from a limits point of view.
One of the things that cloud does really
well and is shaved shaped the industry
is
if you let a service like AWS Lambda
just simply say you know what you can do
100,000
containers from now at any point in time
just send a request and we we'll come up
with infrastructure for you. When you do
times a few million customers you're
going to have to do a lot of capacity
planning and it could also be the wrong
way. Why do you need even need 100,000
containers from the first application
you have? It doesn't make sense. So the
limits help you to put that soft guard
rail to figure out, oh, okay, you hit
the limit. We can increase it. There's
no problem. This is fake money anyway.
>> But let me learn how are you actually
using it. Are you using the SOT model
only? So it becomes more educational and
it comes from a different curiosity
point of view as opposed to my way is
our way. This is our gate. This is like
the way we should be doing it. So this
is becomes more of an IT service as
opposed to platform engineering.
>> Gotcha. So it's really you are giving a
lot of autonomy and ownership to
engineers but you have a conversation
point kind of built in because there's
always a budget when it comes to what
what you can use right if you want to
use Intelligj there's a license cost. So
internally there's a budget and with
models state-of-the-art we now have pay
as you go. So there's probably a cap on
there somewhere. And when you hit the
cap there, you have your conversation
starter to talk about, okay, are you
only using state-of-the-art models or
can we do this smarter in a way? So
that's where you hit education
>> pretty much. We also do we as in as a
company, but it's all platform
engineering all their credit nothing to
do with [laughter]
>> is they are thinking they have their own
internal website with patterns. This is
what people are actually doing with AI.
This is are some of the if you use
opensp spec this is what makes
successful. These are some of the people
in the company that you should talk to.
This is how this is a guide for when to
use the very large model. This is a guy
when to use mid-tier models, smaller
models, openweight models, that sort of
stuff. So it's written there.
>> But in this day and age very few people
read.
>> So then it becomes this convers this
self-fulfilling not so self-fulfilling.
It becomes a loop in itself where now
you hit a limit. Let me get close to
you. trying to work it out. Maybe you
didn't even know that that guidance was
there to begin with like solution
engineering like forward deployed
engineer that we call these days or
maybe the guidance is not enough it's
mostly implicit and how do we make this
more explicit maybe we need more tools
maybe we can do something which I'm
experimenting now called autoizer before
you do a task before the agent goes
ahead and implements like let me do this
I'm the hero um maybe think it through
does he need a spec or does he f just do
ad hoc prompting M
>> again it's never deterministic 100% but
at least it's something that you can add
>> to not make it look like
>> no you can only do this these are your
options
>> this never stopped anyone from creating
shadow
>> they will still go absolutely yeah very
stubborn stubborn folk the [laughter]
engineers
>> no I like that as well I'm thinking
similarly in my context how do we make
these practices scale in the end and I
have the same thought as you someone
hits kind of a budget cap conversation
starter can we Can we educate? Did you
know about X Y and Z? For me, in theory
that works, but when we're talking about
1400 people, how do you scale these
types of conversations? Have you thought
about that as well?
>> Yeah, I mean, again, privilege
[laughter]
for AWS, I managed to I think back in
the days I trained like I don't know
8,000 plus architects back in the days.
uh because I was lucky enough to be one
of the first uh then
there's a time for patterns and a read
it before anything else or try to use a
to summarize it for you if you don't
want to read it. Um there are tools that
will make your life easier because you
want to codify these things as much as
possible like I did with power tools. If
you codify it to a point where this stop
part of the workflow, people won't even
get surprised by the time they hit a
limit or something for instance and then
you have the normal like internal
meetups, internal community building if
you will and building the ideas of
champions everywhere. Uh not only at a
we are trying to do this as well but
Amazon was very notorious for doing
this. Uh one of the things I loved about
Amazon was when you go to an interview
for instance you would have the concept
of a bar raiser. So we have someone
who's been very very experienced in
interviewing lots of people call
hundreds of people and they will not be
in your team and let alone in your
organization most of the time they'll be
completely outside but you will know
that you could trust that if they earned
that accreditation if you will you know
they're going to have a high bar. So
this idea of champions like training
certifications and tears does pretty
well is the same pattern. It's nothing.
What we're dealing is nothing new. Uh it
just the speed of how you can hit the
road and hit the wall.
>> It chang it. But the way you approach
it, the way you look at things is the
same.
>> Gotcha. I like that. It's not just we
only do this. We do this and this and
this and this to make sure we have
enough bases covered where we're
confident in educating people making
sure they are feeling enabled and
equipped to work on whatever outcome
they are responsible for cuz that's
really enablement
>> pretty much if you look at the software
as you if you will which I really love
to do it when I was doing power tools
with the team and with the community I
never did it alone I my biggest
challenge was how much is is
opinionated.
How much is this just an opinion because
we think we're right cuz it can happen.
Egon happens everywhere. And how much do
we simply leave them to make a decision
on their own and just give them the
basics. This is like always been the
hardest thing. So when you look at
software and think if Java gives you all
these standard libraries and a bunch of
things like Python and Go and so forth,
why do people keep using frameworks?
most of the time is like you don't want
to make decisions. You want to make as
very few decisions as possible. So once
you figure that out in your own context,
in your own problem space, what is it
that you don't want to make a decision?
What is it that people get you decision
fatigue? Like this is nothing to do with
them. This is not going to change
drastically the outcome. Then you codify
this and you automate this and remove
the the decision. So agents basically is
the same. The idea of the road map that
we just discussed, the idea of having
something that would act like a thinking
partner in a in a very aggressive way,
in a socratic way, uh all the way to a
gate, which we talk it we'll talk
through about merge checks, which
everyone myself initially hated, but now
I'm improving.
>> Yeah. uh is there to save you from from
those things but it's also there to not
force you to make that decision because
there's only so many decisions we can
make in a single day before we already
are tired before all the walls of text
we are reading from agents are producing
it so these things get to you
>> gotcha yeah what's next in this workflow
>> the next piece we have is the the actual
plan once you figured something out you
know what you need to do then the
OpenSpec plan creates the actual
artifacts. So this would be the
standard. There's a spec to this.
There's a design document and there's a
task. We don't use the vanilla open
spec. I learned that we can the most the
biggest power of OpenSpec is that you
can codify the workflow you want, which
is amazing because you're always going
to have a spec that has to happen.
Everything else you can customize. You
can add many gates, many artifacts, a PD
if you wanted to. And that is the phase
where we now introduce things like
formal verification which is a way for
you to specify how your system should
behave. What are the invariance? What
are the states that should never happen
to begin with? Think an outbox pattern
where you add something to the database,
a transaction, and then you also add a
item that you can use as a queue. For
instance, you put an event or something.
And that outbox typically would always
be something like it has been persisted
or is in the process of being persisted
or it failed should be retried.
>> So there's nothing if something happens
outside of this it's wrong. So you can
codify these things using something we
use something called FSBY which I really
love but there's many others TLA plus
squint. So when you do this is more
precise for agents to know what needs to
be done at implementation level because
English is like for us humans is never
precise.
>> So this plan creates all these things at
once. It creates the spec enumerates all
the acceptance criteria because it came
from the road map. He enumerates what
are the what are the outcomes that
something we want to do the entire
design goals non goals what is the
testing strategy what are we using in
add testing for do we need do we need
fuzzing testing do we need property
based testing unit test is a given but
what else do we need and are we creating
test for the sake of test or do we
really need to all the way to is this
covering UI changes if it does cover UI
changes what are the components we're
going to use are we going to run
contrast testing for accessibility and
some of these things. So the design is
very comprehensive and it's something we
customize. So the agents just look at
this and got it. And then the task is
basically a atomic version of this. So
do this first and we're going to do this
backend first the API and it also covers
things like if this is a breaking change
what is our migration strategy as well.
How what do you do first? What can you
do in parallel? What can you do
sequentially? Would your advice be to
start with openspec and then indeed look
at what you think is important within
your software development life cycle and
codify that as much as possible or are
there frameworks out there or
open-source sources where people can get
inspiration to kind of get a head start.
What I would always recommend is start
simple and then you you bring your own
thing. The mistake is to choose
openspec TLC which is really good. It's
some of the most advanced right now or
using Amazon key or something that's
already baked in and use that as the
only way because everything works
differently inspection AI
hyperpersonalization. So the beauty is
to start so you understand the cycle of
a specdriven development. So you're
going to have to have a spec, you're
going to have to have a design and
you're going to have to have tasks.
That's the that's the essence of it. But
the quality of what your design looks
like, the quality of the additional
tasks that you can do, this has to come
from you. So you can start with
anything. Opensp spec I think is the
simplest. You just install Openspec and
then just open spec explore and you
guide you with everything. Don't have to
do anything else.
>> But don't stop there. If you stop there,
that's a mistake because then it means
either you probably don't have a process
and you probably haven't taught too much
about software correctness. So the
default will basically be as good as the
model that you're using it and that's no
good.
>> Yeah. How fast did you start with
vanilla openspec to what you have now?
How much time was in between kind of
codifying [snorts] the thoughts that
people have the opinions of the
organization and the people driving it.
>> So this the initial version of openspec
to a custom workflow took me like a
month.
>> Okay.
>> But to get to a point okay this works in
a team that took a good three to four
months.
mostly because I was like anybody else
oppos
everywhere and I'll just use it and then
the moment I start using every iteration
was like oh there was like 50 million
tokens
>> and I was like I did one which was a
refactor of how I was doing front end
I'm doing something I really love now
called local first architecture which is
like my god I wish I had known this
before and this cost me like almost 200
million tokens to refactor and I'm like
[clears throat] oh I need to stop using
ous doesn't work. It's
>> junky.
>> Exactly. And the moment I tried to use
uh open weight models, think Kimmy,
think uh GLM or something. This was like
four months ago.
>> The implementation was like so worse uh
quality start lying to me think even lus
lies as well. And that's why it took a
lot more time. I can codify these
things. But the moment I try to save on
those tokens and use different models,
it's like using different frameworks,
it's like using different programming
languages. So I have to be very careful
to learn
how do I now build a verification loop
which is now called loop engineering.
[snorts and laughter]
Uh so then I can
turn this into more of a commodity
ideally which is ideally where we should
be heading.
>> Yeah.
>> So this took a lot longer. This is where
I spend most of my time. How do I bring
the SOTA models right here, the
state-of-the-art models and then bring a
mid tier and then I bring a very cheap
model to do reviews.
>> Are you capable still? That took a lot
of back and forth. The piece I'm working
right now, which is in part of the the
slides, is I'm building a It's not going
to be perfect. It's never going to be
perfect, but I'm trying to be
perfectionist [laughter]
if I'm honest. I'm trying to build
something that works for let's say
almost all models where I can trust that
even if they forge an evidence, they
forge that they run the test, they try
to copy and paste a results from the
internet, which they do. How do I make
sure that this doesn't happen so I don't
let in code that I didn't have the time
to review.
>> Gotcha.
>> How do I make sure that oh it was just
one more thing? we always do this and
how do I make sure that the biggest
challenge I had was when you go through
this loop you're using open spec and you
spec driven that should gets you like 19
95% quality wise software correctness
wise but there's always going to be
something you want to change and that's
when this slippery slope happens because
you're now going to ad hoc prompting and
now you have to remember to run reviews
to run certain things which now you're
falling apart you're falling prey to one
something I learned at Amazon called
good intentions
you're relying on people to remember,
oh, we need to run these things. You can
do CI gates, but it also goes so far,
too. So, this is the part that I'm
spending most of my time now. I think
it's going to cost me, not cost me, it's
going to be a one month more investment
until I get something that works outside
of my team as well.
>> Yeah, it's like people going off the
paper road that you've defined and
you're trying to have some principles in
place to make sure they actually go back
on track.
>> Exactly like we discussed. Yes. You
don't want to say this is the only road
because it's nobody knows.
>> There will never be only one road.
>> The truth is always fragmented, right?
There are multiple versions of the
truth, you know, except certain facts,
right? We don't [laughter]
>> we don't want to turn this political by
accident. Um but with agents having
every time there's an outage atropic,
every time there's a new model, every
time something happens, I notice there's
a deep in quality. But it's difficult to
measure. It's very difficult to do
benchmarking. I don't I barely trust his
benchmarks nowadays as well and I have
to have something that safeguards me
from this deviations this quality
differences and so forth because we're
dealing with nondeterministic pieces,
right?
>> Yeah. You briefly mentioned LFA local
first architecture and also specifically
mentioned I wish I had known this. Could
you explain that for the listener?
>> Oh man, this needs another podcast.
[laughter]
Um local first is imagine let me do the
other way around.
>> Typically we build architectures where
you have a server somewhere cloud on
premises you name it and you have a
client that will have to um basically
work with that transaction the API
request you name it. You're typically
going to have the API server somewhere
not on the client and on the client
you're typically going to have some
level of caching if you will depending
on what you're dealing with.
But nowadays there are newer
technologies that the browser became so
much more powerful in what it can do.
I'll give you the example what I'm
working on right now and why I had to do
this. This is an engineering challenge.
>> We have offices in many parts of the
globe at a and we have the application
I'm building now helps you. It's like a
clone of the well architected uh tool
but better
at in my opinion like an engineer would
have
that this is built in Amsterdam and
we're on premises even if we were cloud
it would be the same issue now you want
people in Singapore and Chicago and San
Francisco to also do reviews and try to
do live collaboration of a review the
latency alone it's not going to make
certain things fun and it's going to be
hard and sometimes you're also going to
have the issue If if I need to upload a
I don't know 100 megabytes attachment
that's also going to have because
physics come into play. How do you what
you typically would do trying to solve
this issue is easy. I add a CDN code
that serves you static assets and serves
you certain things and it gets you a a
TLS handshake a TCP handshake but it's
not really solving the problem. It's
just basically a band-aid eventually
going to have more problems. So a genius
would think I can just use a distributed
database. Let's use cockroach. Let's
just use Postgres everywhere and just
start adding everywhere. But now you're
basically dealing with a synchronization
issue and now you got a distributed
system. Good luck with this. It's not as
simple as it looks. So the local first
piece was how do I give people in
different parts of the world the same
experience to be as nappy as possible
similar to Git where I do most of the
transactions locally first. So think
about transactional database locally
>> and then [clears throat] I sync the
parts that I actually need and to make
it work. So now you're inverting the
problem and you're creating a
distributed data architecture where the
client is a source of truth now which is
usually unheard of.
>> Mhm.
>> And then you're syncing to the server
because you're going to have to have
some sort of aggregation.
>> So local first architecture is the
principle that everything that you're
going to do is going to do local first
going to happen local first. But it
doesn't prevent you from saying well
this part of the page should actually be
coming from server like analytics makes
zero sense to do things in locally
because you're going to blow up their
storage right so there's new
technologies that's called u opfs orange
in private uh file system if I'm not
mistaken if the server a http server web
server respond with two http headers
called cop and cop I can very long to
explain what them but local first will
tell
This enables the browser to unlock a
feature called um VFS virtual file
system which I can now persist a file in
your machine.
>> Oh,
>> which is amazing. Yeah.
>> But it's sandbox there's a bunch of
restrictions is
>> has to be
>> there's a which is good thing it's a
good thing.
>> Yeah.
>> But what he allows you to do is this
idea of local first. Now when I load my
application called where it can be
anything the first page the shell which
shows you something a distraction to
bootstrap download a SQLite web assembly
that will install on your machine create
a new database run all the tables
migrations and so forth in a few minutes
100 milliseconds and now every
transaction happens locally.
>> Okay.
>> And now your server becomes more of a
sync engine. Yeah.
>> Less [clears throat] of the whole very
large APIs and so forth. This makes the
whole experience feels like this is
amazing. This feels like really snappy
like it very looks any latency because
everything's happening locally.
>> It brings different challenges. Release
has now become
>> like open source in a way like you you
do not break the client, right? You have
to think about self-healing from the
get-go. You have to think about
migrations more carefully. You but you
have so many other benefits as well.
Your server, your API becomes much
leaner. You have what? You have a
bootstrap, you have a pull pull, you
have a push and you have a workspace
projection for only to sync the data for
that particular user based on
authentication, based on authorization.
>> I I will have to look into this. This
sounds fascinating.
>> It is. I'm like I'm really loving it.
It's I so much that I I pointed an agent
to uh the the project I'm working on
right now and I said look I want another
local forest architecture with the
privacy first in mind. So there's no
database no server whatsoever.
Everything happens locally
>> as a tool to help me prepare for midyear
and annual performance reviews. So I
have my own like uh record of
achievements local first app.
Everything's happen locally to me
database there. If I want to export, I
create a dump and it's fine.
>> Gotcha.
>> It's that's why another podcast. There's
a lot to dive into.
>> I know I'm just I'm just trying to
digest this. If you want if you're
listening and you want an LFA local
first architecture followup specifically
with Hitler, let me know in the comment
section. [laughter] Yeah, let's go back
to the development life cycle dev loop
that we have here.
>> Yes. So we we talked about the plan on
creating those ar those artifacts like
the design the spec and the tasks and
why you should not
>> settled for the vanilla approach of
using opensp spec or any framework for
the matter but the go the secret is to
codify your workflows your teams and
eventually your company right and then
you got to the apply which is
effectively the implementation one of
the tricks here for any spec driven
development is that your context is now
quite filled with a lot of information,
but because you already externalize that
context into artifacts design so forth,
you don't need that baggage anymore.
Otherwise, you're going to spend more
tokens every round, every turn it takes.
>> So, the apply is simply a moment where
you say,
>> "Let me clear the context." Yeah. Switch
the model to something more mid tier or
lower model if you will
>> and let it execute. Now, this can go for
>> all the way from 10 minutes all the way
to maybe two hours depending on how
complex this thing is. uh especially how
many loops you have and so there's
nothing really secret more of a
autopilot now completely autonomous
you're not in the loop the agents is
driving everything yeah
>> and you can drive
>> multiple sub agents you can do
orchestration you can do anything you
want but openspec doesn't do anything
secret it's just basically saying agent
these are artifacts go
>> that's basically what happens I think
it's the simplest part
>> I think it's fascinating that this
concept of loop engineering and when
people say I don't code anymore or it's
easy to say, right? But if we look at so
far kind of this workflow of discovery
breakdown in items and then the the
preparation, the customization, the
guardrails already up front before that
loop starts running is a lot of stuff
that is pre-prepared.
>> 100%. I think it's the biggest lie to
say even when um the marketing and the
hype came out and saying we don't need
engineers anymore. This problem is all
solved. It was the same when I was doing
service. I was on the other side of the
tape onto the provider and they said,
"Well, you don't need many CIS admins
anymore, many DevOps folks anymore
because you don't need them to look at
the server operations anymore." But it
doesn't mean that their time is not no
longer valued because it just moves
higher up the chain.
>> Coding was never really the bottleneck
for the most part, but there was still
very difficult coding that he was the
bottleneck. We cannot lie. Especially
C++ and a bunch of things that my god, I
don't miss this. Uh
but
the value of thinking about what the
problem is, how do we break it down,
who's the customer, what the outcome is,
how do we make it part of the business
otherwise we're just playing, right?
every developer before they became a
developer dreamed of I would just code
all day when they reach enterprise or
they reach corporate like I'm mean
meetings all the time like yes because
coding is part of the problem part of
the whole supply chain if you will but
it's not the biggest part
>> and the same for agents now I it came
out today actually it was uh the blog
post one of the most anticipated blog
post about how did bun which is a nojs
runtime if you willish
rewrote from zigg to rust
>> and how we prepare the whole code base
the patterns boring patterns that's
basically what we're doing
>> when people say I don't code anymore I
barely do anything and create a loop
there's all this preparation because the
agent starts fresh every time even if
you create a memory MD or whatever
people call these days
>> it has to know what good looks like
>> I was really looking forward to this
blog post so I'm happy it's out
>> yeah it came out this I was [laughter] I
was on the commute I was like yes
>> I have to I have to read that as So
there has been comments that people said
specdriven development working with
agents there is so much work up front
that I would rather do it myself or I am
faster manually and I think this work
that you do up front for me is like an
investment right you invest early
>> you reap benefits months down the line
and it can be quite quickly if you're
like I'm not going to invest but I'm
just going to save and it's going to sit
on my bank account then yeah at some
point people are going to have bigger
returns higher dividends
bigger reap of rewards on their
investments they made early on. For me,
this is quite comparable. So, it's it's
a shame where I see people not investing
in not just their own workflow, but how
does this scale in teams or in
organizations or thinking and
experimenting because right now
everyone's experimenting. So, right now
is the time to experiment. I would say
this is the discussion we're having
about um
investing in adjacent roles or SKs in
adjacent places. So, you can use this.
I'll give an example for this. When you
we do an apply, one of the tasks at one
of the very few and at the end of the
task that we do is something called a
update decision log and we keep a a log
of every decision we made in the project
with the reason the why almost like an
ADR but a very lightweight one
>> and yesterday I created something I'm
very proud of as I still have two more
to create but now still thinking about
how do we think about open source at a
so forth it's called slash onboarding is
a command as a skew as
where you you will try to scan your
project for the likes of code owners,
git log, git branches, docs, opensp spec
if there's any or any spec for that
matter and then we will give you a high
level review of how what's the
architecture of the project is what are
the main decisions what are the stable
areas of the project unstable areas who
are the people that are likely know more
about this area that you should talk to
and then guide you through a
personalized on boarding. Do you know
nothing about this? you know some areas
you want to dive into this area do you
want me to create an interactive HTML
and you go from there so this
investments usually pay off when you
think about teaming based and if you
come from an open source uh background
you're always thinking how do I make it
easier for someone to contribute
>> but also how do I make it harder for
someone malicious to try to contribute
something they shouldn't be contributing
to begin with
>> so agents are not so different from this
>> gotcha I also wanted to make it explicit
this is the first time where it's just
is just agent right running in a loop
and you mentioned it could be 10 minutes
it could be 2 hours have you thought of
where the agent runs is that locally on
someone's laptop is that remotely so
they can shut something down they don't
have to have their laptop open I see
memes with people walking and their lid
is like a little bit open so the agent
can still run in these loops
>> what are your thoughts on that
>> we do everything locally today we have
experiments going on trying to run into
a remote machine and so forth but I
would say we're very early on this one
Uh it's not very different from remote
developer machines. I used to work with
media companies uh back in the days uh
like broadcasting companies back in
London and some of those were used to
use remote developer machines as a way
as a safety measure. For instance, you
lock everything down and so forth. But
he also creates a friction when it comes
to developer experience certain things
you can do.
>> So I don't think we're there yet. For
now all of this is running locally.
>> Yeah. They except the last parts where
we do additional review gates which it
happens with a tool I'm really loving
enough. It's not a full endorsement by
the way.
>> I'm not sponsored. [laughter]
>> It's called code rabbit.
>> If you want to sponsor me, let me know.
>> True. Yeah. So those things are becoming
more and more useful now. What happened
at the CI site?
>> Gotcha. And when you say local, is it
then still in some type of sandboxed
environment or do people run the risk of
this loop kind of going ham? And we
prevented that by all the work up front.
>> Not not neither of those. So it's still
local, but one of the we're dealing with
agent, right? We're dealing with money,
>> money movement, and a bunch of things.
So we need to be very careful in what we
do.
>> Um
there's tools like factory droids where
you can have enterprise governance for
instance. You can prohibit certain
levels of commands, certain levels of
things should be used. Even if an agent
tries you say prohibited or sometimes
you will say oh uh this is actually uh
advised against by organizational policy
I need your explicit permission to be
able to run this for example. So there
are levels of these things
>> even for agentic workflows. Yeah,
>> especially for that.
>> I'll give you an example. As soon as you
start using [laughter] agents and use
Kubernetes and agent was like, "Yeah,
let me just delete this bot. Let me just
delete this thing.
>> We need to
>> Yeah. [laughter] So you kind of can't.
Okay.
>> Uh let me try to remove the entire
directory of home directory." So you
just can't.
>> Good.
>> Uh so there are things that you can do
nowadays with AI and enterprise with
governance.
>> Yeah. And factory droid is something
separate from the open source droid
agent harness, right?
>> Yes. So the droid itself is the harness
which is kind of open source but all of
these companies now are investing into
this enterprise governance if you will
open code from DAX is the same idea as
well. So
>> the harness is where you do all these
amazing things
>> but you but like any remote development
environment in cloud you're going to
have to have policies somewhere.
>> Gotcha. Interesting. I'm also going to
look into this. We we have been
investigating kind of local sandbox
environments where we want people to
have comfort and more confidence running
agents for longer times, right? If it's
5 minutes, it's okay. You can still kind
of look at your screen and be like,
"What is it doing?" But when we're
talking about 2 hours, no one's going to
sit for 2 hours and stare at the screen
to make sure it doesn't delete the home
directory. And if it does, you might
still be too late cuz you were sleeping.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you want something in place.
>> Yeah. We heard stories about this, but
yes, I mean, you can you can use hooks
in literally every harness right now to
prevent some of those things,
>> but you're not dealing with if you're
dealing with a few developers, sure. But
if you're dealing with thousands of
developers, then the conversation
becomes different.
>> Yeah. I want to zoom into hooks since
you mentioned that. For me, let's let's
start with what what is a hook to to
make sure the listener understands.
>> Sure. So, a hook similar to anything
that happens in your machine, it usually
generates an event of a kind. Sometimes
it's a log, sometimes an instruction to
a computer to follow and off of that off
of that event something will happen. So
if you're running an agent on your
machine through open code, cloud code or
codeex or any of those things or factory
droids, there are certain decisions or
checkpoints if you will that those
events will be emitted. So before I run
a tool, after I run a tool or I'm
running the tool or something like this,
you can intercept that event and say on
top of the instruction you were meant to
do, do this other thing. So for
instance, you can say before you return
the control to the user to say I've done
it, run pre-commit hooks. So you know
for sure they're always going to be run
it. But it's not a smart way to do it. A
smarter way to do is to do at the
pre-commit hook. So if git is going to
make a commit to this, it's going to tap
into a hook event that you can now run
certain commands and to say abort this
operation. So the hook is basically
event driven but from a process from a
tool point of view.
>> Mhm. And does it does a hook run when a
loop is done or does it run with one
iteration of a loop?
>> It would it depends on where
from the one we just discussed. will
typically be from an iteration of the
loop.
>> Yeah.
>> But you typically want to have your own
hooks baked if in in some ways. A loop
is nothing more but a hook in a way.
>> Gotcha. For me, the the concept of hooks
are incredibly powerful.
>> I want my code to be easy, simple to
change. I've said that many times. I've
been inspired by one of the guests to
say that. And you still want that when
your agent is performing the code
execution for you, right? when you're
not doing it hands-on but when your
agent is typing the code or generating
the code rather. So those conventions of
code quality standards specifically in
our repository or for a paved road for a
specific technology I think we should
move that as much as we can in
determinism and hooks are a way to do
that right your linting or sgrip rules
I've seen people do things with or
making sure there's certain security
standards that are there or as much as
you can conventions so the code is more
predictable in terms of its quality
structure architectural decisions
Because in the end, I also feel like
this investment is going to pay
dividends because someone has to review
that code. And if you continuously have
to review structure, you're going to
have so much fatigue because we can go
extremely fast in generating code. But
when you have to review everything like
it was written from scratch by someone
who has no idea what they're doing and
does not adhere to any of the
conventions or it's more of a coin flip,
sometimes yes, sometimes no, you lose
your edge and you lose your cognitive
load quite quickly. I'm smiling because
I the reason I spent this um the last
few months which I mentioned that was
the hardest to make it team based is
because I codify this exactly what
you're mentioning now which is we're
going to call it at the end of this uh
this this image called slash retro.
>> Yeah.
>> Um when we do this continuing this when
we do the implementation of it you
typically do this ad hoc prompting if
you will to fix certain things you don't
like the way the test was structured. It
doesn't matter how many SKs you have, it
will happen. It's bound to happen. And
that's when the quality gaps are
happening. And that's when you start
losing the trust a bit on whether he's
doing what you're what you're supposed
to be doing, the quality gates and so
forth. Is this more deterministic? How
do you bring some of these things? The
way I'm solving this now is in two ways,
two checkpoints, not hook.
We run as part of the openspec plan we
run roughly 15 adversarial reviewers for
the changes are being made. So think is
Python code being touched? You're going
to run a Python adversor reviewer go
same TypeScript same Postgress wait look
at the queries that are being created or
look at the DDLs that are being created
for the way creating tables already are
making changes this is going to cause
data loss the reviewer will be able to
catch it. So you run all of these things
locally, but we can also run at the CI
and this will generate an attestation
like we do in in high stake releases
like I used to do in open source that
every release it would generate an
attestation in a provenence to prove all
the steps that it took to be able to
generate that release to begin with the
CI/CD the jobs the environment variables
commands and so forth all recorded and
I'm doing the same idea from for as a
merge check to prevent agents to
fabricate evidence that they run tests
that they did things that they were
supposed to do. So every change, every
commit that you do would always have to
accompany a cycle of a review based on
the changes. So think you have a floor
of always running security reviews. They
always have to happen
>> always.
>> But you're also going to have
conditional reviewers like is this if
it's not touching Python, why would you
run it? If it's not touching
documentation, why would you run it? So
I have this kind of a floors from
security and outcome verification and
also a conditional one that would run as
these things run and I have a
deterministic scripts that would verify
if they actually run. Did they actually
read those any files the hooks and a few
other things if they did then we can
generate an attestation with all the
evidence to test the findings the things
that need to be fixed and this gets
validated at CI which premputes
everything. It's a bit more complex than
this but this is the simplest form I can
do. That's why I'm calling a merge
check. Once this happens, after we
conclude this whole development cycle,
the biggest learning I've had over the
last 6 months is you tend to forget that
because agents are doing everything for
you, some of those things could be
deterministic.
But after you run a session for like
three, four, seven hours, you're
exhausted. The last thing you want is to
think about what could this be a
llinter? What could this be a custom
rule or something or formatting rule?
You just forget. So I built a command
with expiration from an Icelandic
company from a friend of mine called /
retro where you're having the same
socratic method
>> but looking at the last session or the
current session you just had and figured
out what is it that you had to course
correct the agent because you went
ballistic, you went haywire or you
didn't do what you actually wanted to do
or things that you had to fix mentally
because you know the agents sometimes
doesn't do that much as a good job. It
happens or that it simply you don't know
how to make this more deterministic.
>> So what this retrocomand does is
interviews you. It looks into your whole
context and sessions and so forth and
figures out these are all the threads I
can notice that we can have the
discussion. We can dive into this and at
the end this is a table of everything
that could be made deterministic now
>> and everything else that could actually
be nondeterministic but more lightweight
less instructions or less something and
this is how I used to improve this whole
loop of development to introduce a merge
check to introduce one reviewer at a
time to introduce custom linting roles
to introduce architecture guards to
prevent a file importing some other file
that shouldn't be because we're using
ports and adapters and such.
>> So, it kind of becomes a continuous
improvement.
>> I was actually thinking since we've gone
through this and there are tidbits that
I want to put into practice myself first
and foremost, but I also think from a
listener's perspective, they might want
to try this out. Are you planning to
open source this? Is this available?
Where can people find this? [laughter]
This is not yet open sourced. Uh, but I
can make a comment on YouTube video
after the fact uh with a sample of what
it is. uh but we are discussing
how ways of doing open source at engine
and not only this work there's retro
there's on boarding I'm now doing
offloading when you're going when I go
for holidays for instance or when you
got just got back from vacation there's
a few little tricks that you can do or
even our own openspec custom workflow
with all this merge verification loops
if you will framework that I'm trying to
build
>> we're looking into this but if you were
to try Now it's could be as simple as
instruction as [snorts] you are a agent
specialized in help me reflect and find
optimizations for my development
workflow. Your job is very simple to
look at into my context. Look into my
previous session or my current session
and ask me if I have any notes or what
went wrong, what didn't go so well.
Interview me. Use socratic method. Find
the threads until there's nothing left.
Once you have a better picture and you
know precisely there's no other
outstanding topics or if the user says
so then create a table showing what
exactly could be made deterministic so
my user or us spend less effort less
fighting less frustrations because we
have a life outside job as well
and what is it that could be additions
to our nondeterministic ways of doing
things could be a reviewer could be
something else. So make it look nice and
it's just a simple table that you can I
the user can ask questions if if needed
>> and that's basically what wet is like 30
lines if I'm honest but just that
thought of having something that you you
can call at the end of a session or
maybe after two three sessions I don't
know keep notes somewhere on paper or I
just keep a note like uh retro.md out in
my home directories I keep notes of my
frustration my frustration and things
like, "Oh my god, Opus was doing fine.
What happened here?" [laughter] It
happens. Um, and and I feed this later
during the retro and then he keeps
finding an amazing things.
>> But I have to warn you that if you're a
perfectionist like I am, you're going to
want to keep running these retros for a
long time. And then sometimes you might
get to bring your pragmatism a bit more
because there's always going to be areas
to improve. There's always going to be
ways to do things. But for me, my
favorite is moving from, oh, I love
these agents. I trust these agents. And
now agents are actually not doing the
things they're supposed to be doing.
Then it goes into this trust and uh the
loss of trust and recovery uh idea. And
then for you to get back to the baseline
of the trust you had, it never gets
there. It will increase slowly as it
gets right. But this idea of a retro
start moving. Maybe I could do a custom
linting rule to prevent writing test
this way, writing code this way. I
learned recently in Go that we have the
Golen CI uh linked tooling that you have
a dependency guard feature that retro
told me about and I was like yes you can
do this thing. So then this there's the
import will never happen and your binary
remains less than 3 megabytes. I'm like
>> perfect let's just do it. So this is
something that's going to be highly
personalized. So it goes back to the
premise of if you ever worked in open
source before. It's an edge for you
because you're always trying to think of
how do I make it easier for someone to
contribute maybe the first time maybe
recurrent. How do I prevent malicious
actors or even yourself in a bad day in
a tired day it will happen
>> from
that risk to get into your project. But
what we missed in open source was
this idea of I'm getting close to my end
of my day. My battery is running low and
I can remember these things. But you now
have a log of everything that happened.
So now I can use an agent to do what
they do best. Look up heaps of data,
lots of things and find meaning
somewhere there.
>> Yeah, this kind of self-inter looking at
my session logs and improving from
there. I feel like I can do that. And if
I revert back in time, if I was doing
this when I was early in career, I feel
like this agent and this way of giving
feedback is going to have me make a lot
of decisions. A lot of decisions that I
don't even have a clue on how to make,
right? Oh, did you know X, Y, and Z? You
can do this in this llinter. I'm like,
well, I didn't even know what we're
doing right now. So, how much do I need
to use my own critical thinking or how
much can I let the agent kind of also
advise me and inform me and kind of be
my guider there? What's your advice?
>> It would it would always be a a bit of
both, right? I'll give an example that
happened yesterday. Yesterday I was
refactoring a I'm building an entire CI
automation for GitLab because I I miss
dearly GitHub in certain aspects of
things. Um
and I I wanted to have a way for anyone
in the company at agent to say include
the merge check includes as attestation
to make sure that the agent are not
lying to you fabrication but it's
supposed to be just a single line. So
this but I also want to have protections
at alter code altering time to prevent
this part of the code should have no
side effects. There should be no calls,
networking calls, io's should only be
saying this is the hook I received or
event I received and add a label that
should be an action remove a label or
something then something else would
control the side effects makes it easier
for test make things testable. What the
agent understood was okay sure no
problem one line fine and then he
created an entire refactoring plan where
he was like all you need is two docker
images and all these different
deployments three different repositories
I'm like no [laughter] I like that
you're thinking about docker images have
it self-contained but for there's three
different concerns here one of them is
customer first how do I make it so easy
that they just include and that decision
fatigue goes goes away. Second, how do I
prevent myself from accidentally editing
things that I shouldn't be editing? So,
my architecture that started well and
now became a spaghetti, but also how do
I prevent an agent to basically lie to
me and start editing these things
because they have free will to a degree,
right?
>> And then the last one is how do I make
this deployment easier so it doesn't
become a burden for me to now maintain
this whole thing because complexity
never goes away. You're just shoving it
somewhere else. I don't want to deal
with that complexity even though I'm
trying to make it as easy as possible to
the user. If that's going to be an
uneven calculus, then I want to shift
the balance a bit more. And then that
critical thinking has to happen.
>> This is where sometimes it's hard for
new engineers or engineers that haven't
been long enough or have made enough
mistakes. I made more than I can count.
uh to be able to have this kind of a
forward thinking look and then say
actually agent you did great for now but
don't do this. The way you can counter
this balance if you don't have enough of
experience to have critical thinking or
to read enough code or to have enough
scars hopefully don't have that many uh
is [clears throat] to run cycles of
adversarial reviewers. So you can always
say for instance bring Fable and say use
our judgment to when to launch other
lower model less capable models than you
to review the work that you're doing and
then bring from a security point of view
from a customer point of view and this
is something that I even accidentally
discovered that you can do this from a
product point of view as well. You can
create a PRD. You can create everything
else. And you can say this is the type
of customer I'm trying to get you the
market or the segment. Create a
syntactic customer for this, for this,
for this, for this, and review these
things.
>> So then you get different findings and
then find what's common and then let's
do it. Yeah,
>> it's not going to solve you not having
any critical thinking, but it's going to
reduce like an architect, your your main
role is trying to not only make everyone
else around you smarter, but also trying
to reduce the risk for that decision.
>> Gotcha.
>> So, you can do it with agents as well.
>> Yeah. I love that. Like even as you're
explaining this, you communicate that
this is something I figured out
recently, right? Or something that I
explored and now I learned and then I
put it into practice. It really
highlights that a lot of what we learn
now and even what we communicate is so
fresh that it would be a shame to not
try things out and to experiment and to
learn and to cuz I feel like earlier in
software engineering there was not as
much innovation for me. This is right
now a very cool time to start innovating
to start learning to see what you can
improve and I've been having a lot of
fun doing it to be honest. Yeah,
>> I think so as well. Yeah, I I I'm I'm
having so much because I think the more
experience you have, the more dogmas you
also acrewue and then this age now it's
like actually we could do something
else.
>> I was having this discussion again with
a friend of mine, principal engineer,
brilliant guy. It's like I kind of look
up to him when it comes to rust like
he's the genius of rust.
Um,
one of the things that he's doing,
Nicholas, please uh forgive me for
saying for sharing some of your
brilliant work ahead of time. Uh, but
he's looking at how do we make sure that
we have engineering design discussions
in a structured way in a way that you
can feed it to agents or you can do
other things for instance almost like a
decision of record but heavier on tech.
And when I looked at the document with
him yesterday, one of the things that
struck me was like this is very
Amazonian
>> on having this all of these things so
well thought out that you have to go and
answer and have to go and write. But I
also know from open source that when
people see this they will fear they will
shy away. they will just do the very
minimal or they will probably just use
use shachi pt gemini or whatever to just
try to write it down and then the cold
critical thinking goes out the window
>> what we can do what about I I I showed
him this loop that we're just discussing
now what if we have a skill that uses
that piece or a command I think is
better than sq uses the pieces as a
template as a starting point but use
socratic method and makes this part of
the workflow so Then when you're trying
to do the first brainstorming or explore
opensp spec or whatever now you're
embedding resilience uh aspects to
things. So now you're adding instant
management as part of this thing. So
this becomes natural now [snorts]
>> and this whole document gets produced
without them knowing this was
>> the goal to begin with. Yeah.
>> Similar to open source power tools. The
whole point is for people to just this
is so much easier to use. Add a logger.
Now I got structure logging. Once you
get a correlation ID, just add this
flag. And now at the end when they
review, oh yeah, I'm doing all this. I
didn't even know it.
>> Yeah,
>> this is the aha moment that I I wish we
we move more towards.
>> There's definitely some there should be
some behavior psychology there because
I've also noticed that if you give
people the end result, if the end result
is perfect and they don't trust it, it's
never going to fly, right? But if you
give people tools and they create that
end result themselves, they build
conviction by because they're in the
loop. their critical thinking is used,
they are building their own conviction
by doing, then they really believe in
the end result and all of a sudden you
have automatic buy in. That was the goal
in the first place is like you're good
to go.
>> Pretty much. And that's the whole point
we started the conversation about um
>> why
engineers sometimes focus so much on the
hard skills, which is truly necessary.
You have to, especially agents, you have
to know that they're lying. They're
coming up with suboptimal results. But
when you start going studying adjacent
roles, this is where you start
amplifying yourself. And agents are
supposed to augment you. But first, you
need to augment yourself with all of
those skills. So then you can reach much
[music] higher heights.
>> Yeah, Ira, thanks so much for coming on
and sharing.
>> No problem. This is great. Yeah,
[laughter]
>> thanks for having me.
>> This was the first time we did something
like this, something visual on screen.
So let me know in the comment section
what you thought and we'll see you in
[music] the next one.